It's no secret that our society has a digital device problem. Ninety-two percent of Americans own a smartphone. Research has found that we are more connected than ever before, and yet feel more isolated, more lonely, more depressed than ever before. How's that possible?
Social scientists call this a collective action problem. We all agree that these devices are having a detrimental impact on our mental health, and yet it feels virtually impossible to withdraw from these devices because they are so interconnected in our lives. So what can we do?
Well, good morning. That was a really cool bumper, but this is the first time I've actually seen it. My name is Michelle Meeks. I'm the children's pastor here.
So I'm really excited to be here this morning because I get the best of both worlds. All my favorite kids are in here, but I also get to share some things with you that God has been really teaching me through this message.
And so if you've been here or you've read the newsletter, if you've seen the announcements, then you know that we are starting a new series that is going to focus on that little rectangular device that has become almost
an extension of our body. It is with us everywhere we go. It is the smartphone, whether you like Andrew or iPhone or whatever it is, we almost all have one. The video said 92% of people own one.
Kids, it might be your iPad, it might be a TV screen, but whatever it is, is a digital technology that we spend a lot of time with. If we're honest,
it's become like that best friend that no one wants to admit is our best friend, right? Like, it's always there when we need it.
It never lets us down. It answers our questions decently well, and we keep it close to our heart so that we never have to be away from it.
But if you're honest, deep, deep, deep, deep down in your soul, especially for the kids, I'm a little worried about a revolt about the topic today, but even kids, if you're honest,
there's a part of you that knows we spend too much time on it, and it is not good for us. It reminds me of, you know, around Christmas time
when we see the really sad Humane Society videos of the puppies with, like, the big puppy eyes, and we all feel like we need to adopt a dog
or, like, refinance our house to help the Humane Society? It reminds me of that. We see these images, usually, ironically, we see them on a screen, of, like, the mom
that's on her phone and not paying attention to her kid. We see these images of us spending too much time on our phones
and it hits us in the heart and we feel guilty, but we rarely do anything about it. So, this, these images that you're seeing
are from a portfolio by a name, by a man named Eric Pickersgill. He named these, this portfolio that he made, "Remove." So, when you look at these
pictures, he wants to highlight the disconnection that we have, that we can be in the same room with people that
we love, but have no connection with them, right? We're all doing our same, we're doing our own thing on our phone.
Is there anything you guys noticed about these pictures though? Yeah, there's no phone in their hands.
Sometimes you don't even realize it, but it gives us a chance to look at what we would look like if we didn't have our
phone. What is it that we're staring at that makes us not talk to each other? And this last image is
my favorite. You notice what's coming right at her? These devices are controlling us so much that I would
imagine quite a few of you in this room have been looking at their phones in a situation where you're
driving or you're at a red light and you have that little bit of time and you look and you're
putting your life in danger because you want to look at this phone so much. These are powerful.
A 2024 survey from Pew Research Center said that teens, 38% of you, say you know you spend too
much time on your phone, and that 57% of you had actually tried to cut back on social
media without being asked. That's pretty big. And the parents, the ones here that feel guilty,
like we have these devices and we gave them to our kids, this is me again, and we
know that they're on it too much, but in our defense when we were first handed these, when
they first came out, we didn't realize the damage that they were doing. The problem
is now we know and we feel so far down this road that we don't know how to turn
around and make a change. And the question is, is why is it so hard to
disconnect from our smartphones? A recent survey showed that four out of ten
adults said that they are online almost constantly, and they spend at least 2.5
hours what is called doom scrolling. Everybody here probably knows what that is, where you
get on a video or Instagram or Facebook or TikTok, and you just scroll. There's no
purpose. You're just looking at things, and it sucks you in. Before you know it, you've
spent 2 to 3 hours wasting time. The same study showed that 46% of teens say that
their parents are distracted when they're trying to have a conversation with them
because their parents are looking at their phones, and the reality is, is we
know. We know we spend too much time on our phones, and the question is why? If you
are here this morning and this is not something that you struggle with, and I
know there are those of you out there that you don't struggle with looking at a
smartphone, I would ask you to think about maybe there's another screen that you do
struggle with. Maybe you end up watching news channels far too much, and that sucks
you in, and before you know it, hours have gone by. Or if you don't struggle with any
devices, then I would ask you to pray for us, because this is not just a
small percentage of people. We're struggling, and we need all the prayer that
we can get if we're going to break this addiction that we have. So while
you're here, you be praying. Because the reality is, is what you spend your time on
is shaping you from the inside out. So before we start looking at why we might
spend too much time on this, I want to talk to you about what these next four
weeks are going to look like. So we are doing a 28-day digital detox. So first, what
this is not. This is not a hatred of technology. We are not saying that
technology is bad and evil, and that we should all throw our phones off a bridge
when we leave church, or have like a smashing your phone party. We're not
saying that. What we are saying is that maybe, just maybe, we need to give our
brains a break from the amount of times that we look at the screens. So the
goal is, for, there's different levels. If you look at your bulletin, it gives you an
explanation of exactly some options for the next 28 days. Nothing is required. No
one's getting, well, teens, I can't tell you nothing is required. Your parents are
in charge of that. For most of us in this room, this is a choice that you have to
make. But the goal is, you take your phone, and you turn it back into a phone. You
get rid of the apps that are distracting you. So, social media, news apps, maybe
email. You get rid of the apps that are distracting you for a short period of time, and
you keep the apps that you need. So, directions, phone calls, FaceTime, text
messages, things that are utility devices rather than distractions, for 28 days. The
goal is to take back the control that the screens in our lives have on us. This is
temporary. After 28 days, you can add all of those back on, but the hope is that you
will have a more realistic view of the relationship you have with your phone and
the ability to remain in control of it rather than having it control you. If this
is making you feel anxious, you are not alone. I had many of the same conversations. I'm the one
giving the message, and I was making all kinds of excuses as to why we didn't need to do this, or
it was going to be really hard. Parents, if you're like me, you're like, "I can get rid of
all the apps. I don't care about that," but my kids, entertaining them when they have none of it,
you're not alone. This is a big problem, and so we can be anxious together, but what research
has shown is when you do it in a group like this, it can help, because we're all in this
together, and we can lift each other up, and other churches have done this. We're not the
first church to do this 28-day detox, and those other churches have surveyed people
after, and 100% of people who took part in it said that they were glad that they
did and that they would do it again, probably not right after the 28 days. They
probably needed like a little bit of a break, but overall, they had seen positive
results. Okay, so now that we have the goals in mind, and what the next 28 days
are going to look like, I want to take a deeper look into how we got here. I'm
the type of person that if you tell me to do something, then I won't do it, but if
I understand why something works the way that it is, or I can see like behind the
curtain, I'm way more inept to do what it says. So I want to give us a glimpse
behind the curtain of what is going on that is making us so addicted.
Romans 12:2 says, "Do not conform to the patterns of this world, but be transformed
by the renewing of your mind. Then you will be able to test and approve what
God's will is. His good, pleasing, and perfect will." We are called not to be
changed by worldly patterns, right? God wants to give us a life better
than what the world offers. And when we're consumed by worldly patterns,
it's really hard to hear His voice, because His voice is not in those worldly patterns.
It's better than that. And I think we would all agree on this next
statement, that there has never been another piece of technology in all of
history that is more effective at conforming people to the patterns of
this world than the smartphone. The average
adult screen time is five to six hours a day. The average teen
screen time is seven to nine hours a day. We're talking
full-time jobs spent on this device
that is never away from us. We will turn back and
drive all the way back home if we're on our way to work and forget our phones.
Or our kids will be in a full-blown panic, teenagers, if they
get to school and forget their phones. We are spending our lives
on these devices. So you might have an argument and say, "Yes, but
what I'm doing, I'm listening to sermons on my phone, I'm listening to
shorts about God, and it's really lifting me up." And you might say that
I need that, but the reality is, is it's still not healthy for us.
I have a friend who's a pediatric psychiatrist, and she
said, "Literally, anything that you do apart from
looking at your phone is better than something that you do looking at your phone."
Staring at a wall, better for your brain than looking at your phone.
So even if you're spending seven hours watching sermons, it's still
better for you to go outside in nature and listen to God's
voice apart from this. So
what is God's original design for us? Okay, so
we know we were created in God's image, right? So God's image
is what we are designed after,
and the Bible makes it clear that God
desires relationships.
Look at Genesis 2:18. The
Lord says, "It is not good for man to
be alone." Adam was in the
garden alone, and so God created
Eve to be his wife,
so that he had someone to be connected
to. And then if we look further at
Genesis 3:8, it says, "Then man
and his wife heard
the sound of the Lord God as he was
walking in the garden in the cool of the day,
and they hid from the Lord God among
the trees of the garden." So this,
they're not hiding because they're shocked that God
is in the garden with them. They're hiding because
they've just sinned, and now they feel
ashamed. But it seems
that God had a close
intimate relationship
with them in the garden. That he would go
for walks with them, and that
they would have communication with each other. So what
this shows us is, you
and I were designed to be in connection
with each other. That
is our ultimate design
from God. And
up until recently, that was
the case. Like, we hung out with each other, and we did
things. We still do. But
the relationships that you had were
primarily face-to-face.
Fast forward to today.
In 2007,
July 29,
2007, the iPhone was released.
It promised
closer relationships, right?
You have FaceTime. My sister lived
in Malaysia for two years, and I could literally
talk to her face-to-face from the other
side of the world. You can call someone.
You can text someone.
You don't have somebody's number? That's okay.
Look them up on social media
and you can communicate with them. The
smartphone promised
more of what God designed us for.
More connection, right?
So why do we
feel less
connected than ever before?
Not only that, but it also
gives us so many advancements.
I can turn on my
appliances. I can't. I don't have
that nice of an appliance. But some people can turn on
their appliances at home
from their phone at work. You can
order pizza. You can book a flight.
You can do all these things just like
that. But yet
somehow we feel like we have less time.
We feel more rushed now
even with all the wonderful things
that these can do.
What is really going
on?
Okay, so many of you have heard of the meta
platforms. So these are
the platforms
that design Facebook, Instagram,
and many other apps
on our phone. And recently
they just lost
two really big court cases.
One in California
and one in New Mexico.
The courts argued that the
companies were knowingly designing
addictive systems to build
your attention, to keep your attention
for as long as possible, while knowing
that this was bad for your mental health.
So these meta systems that
designed all of these things
lost court cases
because they were creating
systems to keep us addicted.
So here's what's going on. This is
the behind the curtain thing where you can see
what is happening to you on
your devices that is keeping you so connected.
So the first thing that they
do is they create
a thing called a reward
loop, or a dopamine cycle.
Here's how it works. You guys
will all know this because we feel it.
Every time you get a like,
or you receive a comment, or
somebody adds you or comments
about you on Facebook, you get
a small release
of dopamine. That is the
reward chemical that makes you feel
happy or joy. And so
once that happens, obviously
you want more of
that dopamine release, right? So you
repeat the same behavior. You go back
on your phone, you look for likes, you look for
comments, you look for that video that
made you really happy, or validated
whatever your thing is
that you're hung up on.
And the key is
unpredictability. So
sometimes you go on your phone, and you
see incredibly boring videos,
and you don't really have a desire to go back
on it. But just when you're about to get off,
you see the funniest cat video you've ever
seen, and it keeps you
on. You get that little dopamine hit, or
someone comments about you, or someone likes your video,
or you have so many views, and
it keeps you on. You don't
know if the next time you
get on, you might get that reward.
So you just
keep looking. You
check again, because maybe next time
it will feel good. So that's the
first thing, the reward loop. The second thing
is the infinite scroll.
There is no stopping point.
When we used to go to the movies,
when you go to the movies, or you're reading a book,
there's an end, right?
Sometimes it's like you
feel sad that there's an end. I've read really good
books, and you're like depressed that the book's
over, and you can't hang
out with the characters anymore, but there is
an ending point. You get up from the dark
movie theater, you walk outside,
it's brighter than you've ever seen before,
and you have to let that movie go
and go back into reality. But for
your bones, there is
no real stopping
point. You
just keep scrolling.
Has anybody seen Finding Dory?
Finding Nemo? Just keep scrolling,
scrolling, scrolling, just keep...
You just keep scrolling,
because you never know if that next thing
is going to be the thing that gives you that
dopamine hit, and you don't have that
done feeling.
So you just keep
scrolling. Alright, so that's
one, reward loop. Two, infinite scroll.
Second thing, personalized algorithms.
These platforms, we
all know this, track
everything we do
all the time. They track
what you watch, what you
pause at, what you
skip. They're tracking so
that they can know you
sometimes better than we know ourselves.
They play on our fears and anxieties
so that we stay on something
so we don't have to miss something that
might be the most important thing ever, and if we
just don't look that day
then we're going to be missing
out and our lives will be in danger.
It's not random.
The things you see are not random.
They are tailored to you
in order to control
you. They're not there
so that you get the best. They're there
so that they can keep you exactly
where they have us,
and they've done a very good job of it.
The fourth thing,
social validation and identity,
they know,
they might not know that we were created by
our Creator for this, but they know that
social connection and social identity
is important to us,
and so they play on that.
We now have a measurable
score, if you think about it.
How many people view your videos?
How many likes do you get?
How many comments do you get?
We can base our
value based on what the phone tells us
we are. Do we have the products
that we shop for?
Do we look like this person?
Do we wear this right outfit?
And so again,
they're keeping us connected
with our social validation on this.
And then finally,
when you get that break,
when you finally are sick of looking
at your phone, and you finally get off, and you
put it away, you get that
wonderful notification sound.
And that
is number five. It pulls
you right back in.
Just when you get sick of it, you hear bloop.
Get your phone out, and you're right back
where you started. Well, what if you get a dopamine
hit? What if somebody comments?
What if someone likes it? And you start scrolling.
Again, it is no wonder that we're
spending five to six hours
on our phone with this
pulling us in.
And then finally, it's a habit.
It becomes habit-forming. You get
to the point that you're not even thinking,
and without thinking, you pull
your phone out and go on Instagram. You don't think
I'm going to do this. You just
do it. It's a habit loop.
So what happens is, you get a trigger.
You start like internally twitching
like I need to look at my phone.
And then, action. Grab your phone.
Reward. Your phone's
algorithm knows exactly what you want
to see, and it keeps you on.
So this is the window behind
why we are so addicted
and what is really going on.
If you don't
believe me, you don't
think that this is you,
have you ever been at a
stoplight, and you have 30 seconds
of downtime, and that
trigger is getting to you,
and you're like, "I'll look at my
phone real quick."
That's an addiction. Have you ever been
on vacation, or outside
with your kids, and you're thinking,
I'm going to take this picture, and if I take this
picture, and I make this really cool comment,
and then I post it, then people
are going to think A, B, and C.
So, rather than being fully
focused on that event, you're thinking
about how you can post that event
on your phone. That's an addiction.
That's control that they have over
our lives, and I am right,
that's been all of my
thoughts. I've been there
every single time.
It is controlling us,
and we are playing
their game. The other thing that happened
is that dopamine release that you get,
you're not designed to get it that
frequently. It's supposed to be
something that you work hard for, so you practice
for a sport, and you work really hard
for kids, and then you win the game.
That's what is supposed to
give you that little dopamine
release, but now, because
it happens so frequently, we
find ourselves craving constant
stimulation. You need
these false rewards
constantly, and this means
allowing yourself peaceful,
unstimulated downtime
becomes almost impossible.
We have to fill it with something. We must
be entertained.
But what does the Bible say?
Jesus says in Matthew
11:28-30, "Come to me,
all you who are weary and
burdened, and I will give
you rest." He
doesn't say, "Come to your phone
and look at the next cat video."
He says, "Come to me,
and I will give you rest."
Psalms 26:10 says, "Be still
and know that I
am God." It is so hard
to be still these days.
We are constantly
focusing on
something, and it's hard
for God to give us the rest
that we really need. In
Mark 6:31, Jesus is talking
to his disciples who are exhausted, and they
haven't eaten, and they've been working, and he says,
"Come with me by yourselves
to a quiet place and get
some rest."
Have you tried to go to a quiet
place recently and just let
your mind rest?
It's hard. You feel that
desire to do
something, to fill it with something, and
Jesus is saying it's in those quiet
places that I can give you the rest
that you're searching for.
Hundreds of Scriptures remind
us where our true rest comes
from, but the pull at our fingertips
is so strong that even the
strongest Christians are
having a hard time
finding the source
of true rest.
This entertainment
that we are offered is a gift from God.
He wants us to have downtime and
step away from our work and enjoy
a break, but
the amount of fake gratification
and the addiction
of wanting more is stealing
our lives right out from under us.
Colossians 3:2 says, "Set your mind
on things above, not
on earthly things."
So the question is, why do these companies
care so much, right? Like,
why is this meta company doing
so much to keep us
addicted? And the answer is
time and control.
If they can have your time
and they can control what you see,
then they
have ultimate control, and especially
they can control where you spend your money.
What is important to them?
Your money. How often do
you end up spending money on something
that your phone tells you you need to spend money on
and it ends up being something that
you didn't give you what you wanted? But that's
okay. There's 17,000 other videos
that will tell you this is actually what
you needed that will make you happy.
And when that doesn't,
it's fine. Here's something else that will
make you happy. They have us
living our lives exactly the
way that they want us
because then they
get control of our money.
Okay, so...
So what?
So we spend our money on some things on Facebook
or on a game, right? Who cares?
Is that really that big of a deal? Well, there's
a whole lot more going on. I want you to
look at a graph
from a
recent study
from 2011 to 2021.
This is the
rise in...
So, ignore the
unemployment. That's just part of their graph.
But, you can see, right
around 2009, 2010,
remember the first iPhone came out in 2007,
you see a
dramatic rise
in these things. Internet
use, depression,
social media, smartphone ownership
correlates
dramatically. And this is just
a 2019. It has gotten
even worse. As a matter of fact,
research now shows that one out of
three teen girls has
seriously considered suicide.
Correlating with the amount of
cell phones that we have. And then we look,
and it's not just in America. If you look at
this next graph, the same exact
research was done in
other countries, Russia, Thailand,
Hong Kong, UK, Chile,
Sweden, and it's the same result.
As people are getting cell phones,
their depression, anxiety,
suicide rate are
all going up.
This is a trend
that is global, and while these studies
focus on teens, adults'
mental health is very similar.
These
false dopamine releases
that we're getting, we
start to realize that if this is the
best thing out there,
then what's the point of living? If this
thing that shifts frequently
and dislike and dislike and
comment, if it's the best thing that this world
has to offer, because it's all we
can see, because it's always with us and in our
hand, what's the point of living?
And teens are becoming more and more
depressed, and
unfortunately, suicidal.
Let's take this a bit further. You don't
just have to believe what people are
saying. You can now see
what smartphone use is doing
through brain scans.
Alright, here's four brains.
These are all brains of
people that are addicted to their
cell phone. There's actually a word for it
now. It is called
problematic smartphone use, or
PSU. So this has
become a thing. So what you're looking
at, this part of the brain is the, and
Doc, I apologize for all the things
I get wrong.
This is the prefrontal cortex.
So this part of your brain
is known as like the thinking part
of your brain. It controls your focus,
your decision making, your self
control your attention. It's like the
mom of the brain.
It's the, or dad, or
dad. It's the thinking part of
the brain, alright?
It's in constant communication
with another part of your brain
that is called the limbic
region. The limbic
region is like the toddler of your
brain, okay? It can, it has,
it controls impulse control,
cravings, emotional regulation,
addictive behaviors. It's the toddler
that's on the floor in Target
having a temper tantrum because you couldn't get
that popsicle. That's the
limbic part of your brain. So the frontal,
prefrontal cortex is constantly
talking to the limbic
brain. You want to have a
temper tantrum in the floor because they sold out
of your favorite thing at Target, or maybe that's
just me. And I have my prefrontal
cortex telling me,
"Calm down. They'll
restock it. It's okay."
And instead of having a temper tantrum,
I calm down, right? This is the
communication that's going back and forth
between these two constantly.
What you're seeing in this picture
is an image
of the connectivity between
these two parts. So the thinking
and the emotional part. The colors
represent how connected
these two are.
Okay, so if you see yellow
or red,
see a teeny bit of yellow in one of them,
that means that they're strongly
connected. So the prefrontal cortex
is telling the limbic, "Calm down.
Don't have a temper tantrum in Target.
It's going to be okay." And I calm down,
right? That's yellow and red.
Not a lot of that in these brains.
Then you have green and light
blue. That means
medium connectivity. So we have
some light blue in these, and so
it's not communicating the way that it should,
but it's medium.
It's still, you know, you don't quite
have a temper tantrum. Finally,
dark blue means
weaker activity or reduced
communication. Have
you ever noticed yourself
losing it over
stupid things? And you're like,
"Why can't I control?" Or
kids, have you ever felt yourself
having temper tantrums, or
losing your mind over
something, and you're like, "What is my problem?"
Like, it's because
you're so addicted that that communication
between your limbic
and your prefrontal cortex is limited,
and that's not, it's not
allowing you to calm down. The
best way to illustrate this is obviously
with a clip from inside out.
Seen that movie?
Remember the part when Joy,
Joy, we're going to call Joy the prefrontal
cortex, because Joy's the
calm one, right? She calms everybody down.
She gets them to rationalize. She's like,
"It's okay." She gets
like, shipped out of the main
headquarters, and everything goes nuts.
That's the limbic system
losing its mind,
because it doesn't have Joy
to calm them down. So let's look at this clip
from
inside out of what happens
when our connection is
not going well.
Why is it so weird?
All the islands are down.
No, I would know what to do.
That's it.
Until she gets back.
I found a junior hockey...
...after school.
Look!
What was that?
Uh, because I'm not Joy?
Yeah, no kidding.
Something's wrong.
Should we ask her?
Let's prove.
So, how was the first day of school?
She's probing us.
I'm done. You pretend to be Joy.
Um...
It was fine, I guess.
I don't know.
Oh, very smooth. That was just like Joy.
Something is definitely going on.
She's never acted like this before.
What should we do? We're gonna find out what's happening.
But we'll need support. Signal the husband.
Ahem.
Uh-oh.
What did she say?
Well, oh, oh, sorry.
We left the toilet seat out.
What?
What is it, woman? What?
I'm leaving my significant face in the office.
Where are you going to work?
I don't know.
Oh, awesome.
There's no problem. Just leave me alone.
There is a TEPCOM 2.
TEPCOM 2.
Here he comes. Prepare the foot.
He's in the second position.
We're in your command, sir.
It's set up.
Fire.
That's it. Go to your room.
Now.
Foot down. The foot is down.
Good job, gentlemen. That's been a disaster.
That was supposed to be a much shorter clip. I sent him the wrong one, so you got to watch a lot of Inside Out.
Now you have a very clear understanding of what happens when these two parts of the brain are disconnected.
And of course, what is the one part of your brain that develops longest into up to your 21 years? The prefrontal cortex.
So our children's brains, this part that calms them down, are developing right now, and it's being disconnected.
But because God is incredible and amazing, research shows that just 72 hours away from your phone and these brain scans look different.
So it's that dramatic what is happening to us. The reality is we need to let our nervous system detox.
We were not designed by our Creator to be addicted to our phones.
Remember what Romans 12:2 says, "Do not be conformed any longer to the patterns of this world,
but be transformed by the renewing of your mind." If the world is discipling your mind more than God's voice is,
transformation will go in the other direction. What are the patterns of this world?
Comparison. You find yourself comparing yourself to others and constantly trying to figure out why you're better than them
or why they're better than you. Fear of missing out or FOMO. You constantly worry if I don't look at my phone,
what am I missing out on? Identity, confusion, who you are, what your worth is, anxiety, depression, fear of the future.
This is the patterns of the world that are constantly being thrown at us.
Psalms 119:37 is like the theme of this four-week series.
Turn my eyes away from worthless things. Preserve my life according to your word.
God's design for us is face-to-face interaction, stillness, meditating on his word,
allowing yourself to hear God's voice. How can we make this change?
What if, instead of focusing on the fear of missing out, we desire the joy of missing out?
What if we didn't always know what was going on? What if we didn't know what the coolest thing to wear was?
What if we allowed ourselves a chance to turn off the noise and breathe?
But what if you didn't have to carry the weight of the world on your shoulders and you went for a walk outside instead of looking at your phone?
What if you read your Bible rather than looking at that news article? What if you gave your mind a soul and a moment to rest in God?
What if you prayed and asked God this anger that I feel in my soul? You show me what's going on.
Maybe there's someone that you've been mad at for years, and rather than looking at a phone that's going to validate all that anger
and give you a lot of reasons to be angry. What if you said, "You speak to me."
Maybe He'll give you the ability to look at that person differently than you ever have before.
But if we have no time in our lives to hear God's voice, He can't open this up.
And so we are stuck in this anxious, angry phase, just like the systems designed it to be.
Psalms 46:10 says, "Be still and know that I am God." What if we are still? Stillness is where we hear God, but stillness is disappearing.
If every quiet moment is filled with checking your phone, watching something, or listening to something, we lose the ability to sit with God and hear His voice.
Because anxiety loves noise, but peace grows in stillness.
If this space feels uncomfortable now, as you're trying to make this transition, if you give this a shot and you go into it, it's going to feel uncomfortable.
I was reading a research article, and it says that your brain has these super highways, right?
It's the thing that we've always done. It's the path that it takes. And right now, for a lot of us, our super highway is, I'm bored, I'm going to look at my phone.
But slowly, if you start to make a change, if you make that one step, you'll start to create a path in your brain that's really hard to go down.
But every time you make the choice to not look at your phone, you take a brick from the super highway, and you put it on the path, and you start building this path
so that your brain's automatic resource is not to go down this cell phone path. You start to make a new path in your brain, and it takes time.
And it's going to be harder than you think it is. Trust me. But every time you look away, you take a brick from your super highway, and you put it on the new path.
Jesus is offering something different in our lives. John 14:27 says, "Peace I leave you. My peace I give you. I do not give you what the world gives you."
The world gives us noise. Jesus gives us peace. But peace requires space.
So as a challenge, this week, ask yourself, "What is forming me more? My screen and my savior." And take that one step. Take a brick out of your super highway and put it on a new path so that we can start to gain our lives back.
These hours that our phones are taking are not what we were designed for. But God wants to take our lives back and give us peace. And like I said, the goal is not to get rid of technology forever.
The goal is to get a realistic view of what it is doing to you and then gain your control back so you can enjoy it without it controlling your life. Let's pray. Dear Heavenly Father, I thank you so much for the things